Sweden's history between the 16th and 19th centuries is divided into four eras.
-This is the first of them.
-Vasa time is a revolving time.
It must have felt very dramatic.
The Vasa era is counted from Gustav Vasa becoming king to Karl IX dying.
A lot happened in Sweden then.
A new king changes religion in the country and sends out bailiffs everywhere.
It is a time filled with conflicts with peasant uprising and power matches about the throne-
-Which is quite close to fantasy.
What happened in Sweden during the Vasa era?
And how fun was it for ordinary people?
The 16th century Sweden does not look like today.
Areas are missing in the south and west, but large parts of Finland are included.
In this kingdom, almost the entire population lives in the countryside - 95 %.
Almost everyone lives near a church.
Next to the church were a group of farms with barns, houses and cattle.
The villages were small.
It may have been hundreds or fifty people.
The church, which people live next door, is also not as we are used to today.
Sweden was Catholic.
The church and the bishops had very great power.
The fairs, ie the services, were celebrated in Latin.
Sweden is more Danish than Swedish.
Sweden was part of a union with Denmark and Norway that was ruled from Denmark.
In 1520, Denmark invaded Sweden-
-As now with coercion, the Kalmar Union is kept.
The Danish King Kristian II, sometimes called Kristian Tyrann in Sweden-
-King to king over Sweden.
It happened in Stockholm.
He behaved really badly when he was there.
During Stockholm's carnage, many who could stand up against him were executed.
Who will save Sweden from the Danes?
A clue is found in the name of the era.
A young nobleman does not trust Kristian Ii-
-And stay away from the capital.
Gustav Vasa's path to success was Stockholm's carnage-
-As wiped out large parts of the top tier within the Swedish nobility.
He now has a good position to take power if he can remove the Danes.
In Dalarna he hopes to gather farmers in an uprising, but it goes like that.
Why are they going?
Why don't they listen?
How will Gustav Vasa get the farmers to support his plans?
Stockholm's carnage will come in handy in his ambitions to reach power.
When the stories reach out in the country-
-The farmers are subject to a popular rise to the Danes.
Dalkarlarna rethink their position and close up behind Gustav Vasa.
He becomes the master of the landscape.
Now the liberation war against the Danish Union King can begin.
Go Sweden!
It went pretty well for Gustav Vasa in the fight against Kristian II.
They are allowed to borrow and war on credit.
Some who are happy to lend are the city of Lübeck and Hansan.
They look forward to Denmark getting on ding.
With the support from Lübeck, Gustav Vasa finally stands as a winner.
27 years old he is elected king, and in 1523 he trains into Stockholm.
Now the Danish is definitely defeated.
Sweden is now its own kingdom, and it is now the country is based on real.
It is usually said that Gustav Vasa is the founder of the kingdom-
-And what you mean by that is that he defeated Kristian II.
He focuses on something that has money, the church, and changes religion.
It was not strong religious motives that led Gustav Vasa toward Luther-
-When he needed money because he had large debts to Lübeck.
And, at all, he wanted money for the cash register.
Sweden breaks with the Pope in Rome and carries out the Reformation.
The Swedes are now Protestants, and the riches of the church now become the state.
Religious services are now held in Swedish.
The church becomes a communication channel, from the state straight out to the villages.
Gustav Vasa is pushing for changes throughout the state.
He wants to make Sweden a national prince's state.
He settles in a lot that happens in the kingdom.
He develops the mining and copper and iron will be out of the ground.
Gustav Vasa is aware of the benefits of creating his own history.
It is called propaganda.
The chronicle about his heroic adventure in Dalarna is to be taken with a pinch of salt.
He creates a poster about Stockholm's carnage to remind people of it.
But propaganda does not matter when the people think they behave badly-
-And takes their stuff.
The farmers in the valleys are starting to grumble.
They rise again against the king.
The problem for Gustav Vasa is that now he is king.
This is done in the watch uprising.
Gustav Vasa requires extra tax payments.
Every congregation or parish church should give away a church bell.
When the clock picks come to pick up the church bells, they hit them down.
This leads to severe punishments.
They receive a punishment and the death penalty.
Gustav Vasa has ruthless sides.
He executes people to the right and left and cannot withstand resistance.
But he also likes luxury and flair.
This saddle has belonged to Gustav Vasa.
It is a gilded saddle with decor in the color of the steel.
You can discover seahorses with unicorn horns and mermaids.
It was included in the luxury items that Gustav Vasa purchased in Augsburg 1541.
Gustav Vasa loves trends and fashion.
It should be tight pants and gold.
In an inventory of his wardrobe, he had 52 such headgear.
The German princes are his role models.
Gustav Vasa is a man of power.
He can be brutal, cruel and execute people, but he also has humor.
In all the letters he writes, the person Gustav Vasa glimpses a bit.
He was a pretty nice dad.
Gustav Vasa marries three times and becomes the father of eleven children.
He is a piglet and likes to eat sweets.
He has a toothache with which he is drawn, and he can be grumpy and grumpy.
He has bigger problems than toothache.
Outside the country, it is more and more grimbed against him and his rule.
The most serious of the uprising is the Dacke feud, which is a peasant uprising.
The farmers in Småland have had enough.
The Dacke feud is a pretty kind word for a full -scale civil war.
The feud starts poorly.
Vasa's jacks are not used to fighting in the forest.
The farmers, under Nils Dacke, win many kinds.
But in the end, Gustav Vasa wins.
Nils Dacke falls into battle, and his head is put on a pile.
The drawing is actually designed by an adult.
But everyone did not rebel, but lived their usual lives.
What did a day in their lives look like?
They got up early.
Maybe at four, five.
Then the girls would out and milk.
Then they prepared breakfast.
Porridge and mound.
Bread was included in all meals.
Life was a constant toy with what was the basis for the livelihood.
A work of animals and agriculture.
Children help and there is no difference between work and leisure.
They worked to get hot in the house, food on the table, security and stuff.
Chores change depending on the season.
Sometimes it is the focus on the field, sometimes on fishing, and sometimes on cheese cheese.
Someone took responsibility for the fact that there was food on the table at twelve o'clock in the day.
That was when you usually for the big goal.
They eat with their hands and drink most beer-
-The water is usually dirty.
The beer has lower alcohol content than today.
You had no clock, but you were in control of the time in many different ways.
From the 13th century, medieval cities have often had bell ringing.
A care clock calls at nine, and then it should be quiet.
Then it got dark.
It is difficult for us to understand how carbon black it must have been.
So is the life of most people in sweden-
-What is becoming more and more its own, with reformation and central government.
In 1560 Gustav Vasa, old and fragile dies.
Then is the end of the vase time?
No, because Gustav Vasa has introduced that kings should no longer be chosen.
The crown should instead be inherited, so now his descendants can retain power.
He wanted his sons to rule the kingdom together in good care.
But there were very many different conflicts in the way.
In 1958 a grave opens in Västerås Cathedral.
For example, he wants
Marry the Queen of England.
However, he has a problem.
What was problematic for him was that he was not mentally stable-
-And it is difficult to make a diagnosis many hundreds afterwards.
You talk about persecution mania.
-Is he fool?
-Without doubt.
Johan has less persecution mania, but equally large ambitions of power.
He takes a Polish princess and wants his son to become king in Poland.
They still choose king and are also Catholics.
But King Erik is becoming increasingly tricky.
Sigismund wants to regain his throne but is defeated outside Linköping.
After the battle, Karl King Karl becomes IX in Sweden.
Sigismund remains only king over Poland, something he was not happy with.
The third vasason sits on the throne.
He is recognized by his fun, unique hairstyle.
He reigns with a firm hand and clears those who were loyal to the brother.
Karl is the one that many say is most similar to his father, to the way and appearance.
When he gets a son, he baptizes him to the same name as his father - Gustav.
The Vasa era ends in 1611.
And what really happens?
Well, Karl IX dies in a stroke.
And his son, the only 16 -year -old Gustav II Adolf takes over power.
With the change of power, it has been seen as a new era begins.
The Vasa era has often played a major role in the story of Sweden.
This is a huge picture, made by Carl Larsson.
How we look at history change over time.
The image of Gustav Vasa has been very positive until modern times.
Yes, in modern times, the image of Gustav Vasa has a good, collecting country father-
-completed with reckless pages.
He has been described by some as a tyrant, dictator, or Tony Soprano.
What do we have from the Vasa era more than Vasaloppet-
-Which happens in Dalarna, but neither contains rebellion nor bell theft.
The most important thing is that Sweden is still a Lutheran country.
Many people do not think so much, but it is important.